Roman Petrov

Software development engineer, software architect, team leader.

E-mail: <u>roman.petrov@icloud.com</u>

Phone: +79648638619

• Location: Yoshkar-Ola, Russia

• LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/roman-petrov-78212952/

GitHub: https://github.com/MegusPersonal website: https://megus.org

Summary

I'm a software development engineer with 17 years of professional experience. Over the years, I worked with many languages and technologies, and I'm able to learn new ones quickly, the strong foundation in computer science and algorithms helps me with that. I had extensive experience with resource-limited systems (8-bit computers, handheld consoles), which allowed me to learn a lot about code optimization. My goal as a developer is to create products loved by customers by writing clean code with well-designed architecture. As a leader, I like helping people to improve their hard and soft skills.

Skills

- Software development:
 - Native iOS apps (Objective-C, Swift)
 - Cross-platform mobile apps (Dart, Flutter)
 - Web frontend (JavaScript, TypeScript, React)
- Software architecture design
- Project management (Agile/Scrum)
- Team leadership
- Good communication with not tech-savvy people
- General knowledge of user experience design

Experience

Sep 2016 – Oct 2019: Team leader, senior software development engineer in GXB Development (Yoshkar-Ola, Russia)

- Led the development team of Acroplia a team collaboration and communication startup. Grew the team from 3 to 10 people.
- Helped the owner to define the roadmap and managed the project backlog.
- Improved the product usability and conducted user research.
- Improved the team performance by introducing coding and architectural standards.
- Doubled the performance of a quality assurance team by introducing automated testing tools.

- Created a robust and heavily configurable test passing library (Lua).
- Developed an automatic speech recordings enhancer (JavaScript, WebAudio API)
- Developed core functions of a cross-platform mobile application: chat and collaborative whiteboard (Dart, Flutter).

May 2012 - Aug 2016: CTO, Project manager in Omega-R (Yoshkar-Ola, Russia)

- Grew a cross-functional development team from 3 to 25 developers. Educated junior level developers.
- Raised the team performance by introducing a set of technical standards and building an in-house library of reusable code modules
- Worked as a project manager and wrote software design documentation on key projects.
- Developed an offline data synchronization module for a banking application (iOS, Objective-C)
- Developed and optimized a real-time polyphonic pitch detection and performance evaluation module for a guitar training application. The final version worked 6 times faster, so the app could run even on iPad 2 (iOS, Objective-C, Swift)

Dec 2010 – April 2012: Senior software development engineer in DIGT (Yoshkar-Ola, Russia)

Developed a VoIP web browser plugin and a number of browser extensions (C++, JavaScript).

Aug 2007 - Nov 2010: Software development engineer, project manager in Team Force LLC (Yoshkar-Ola, Russia)

- Grew from a software developer to a project manager, managed the team of 3 developers.
- Improved user retention and install rate of My911 application by redesigning its user interface. Developed Blackberry version of My911.

Education

Specialist Degree in Computer Science (graduated with Honors) — Mari State Technical University, Yoshkar-Ola, Russia (1999-2004).

Languages

Russian (first language), English (advanced level, fluent speaker).